Okay, so in this video, we are going to
introduce the concept of
earned value management.
An earned value management is a
methodology or approach to cost management.
Now, there are many different ways of
valuing your project.
Different industries value projects
differently, right?
They use different math,
different convention,
different formulas, and so and so forth.
An IT project, for example, is valued very
differently to a construction project.
So there's many different methodologies
and conventions out there, but the one
that you need to know
for the exam is this one
called Earned Value,
Earned Value Management.
So in this video, we're going to be
discussing these three terms, right?
These are the three basic earned value
terms, planned value, earned value,
actual cost.
Now, the whole principle behind earned
value management is that everything is
calculated in terms of dollars worth of
work.
Even for example, the schedule.
So in an earned value
environment, you will not say
we are three weeks behind
schedule, for example.
Instead, you'll say something like we're
$100,000 worth of work behind schedule.
So the way they have
the formulas is everything
is basically converted
into a dollar value.
Everything is converted into a monetary
value.
And that's why the first time you look at
earned value, it can be a little
challenging, right, because you're
converting your schedule into a dollar.
And so it can be a little confusing at
first.
I mean, just remember, time is money,
right?
So just think of it that way.
So we're going to go through these three
basic terms, right?
These are the three basic terms.
And then in subsequent videos, we're going
to cover all of the
additional terms as well.
And if you understand these three terms,
planned value, earned value, actual cost,
right, this is a good foundation.
If you understand these
terms, then some of the other
terms, some of the other
formulas are fall into place.
All right.
So let's go through each of these.
So first one then, planned value,
PV, planned value.
Planned value is saying, at this point in
time, how much work
should have been completed?
right, how much dollars worth of work
should we have done at this point in time?
So here's a typical
scenario, right, that you
could get, very simple
typical scenario, right?
So it says you're five weeks into a
10-week project costing $100,000,
you're 40% complete and you've spent
$60,000 so far.
All right.
So if we are five weeks into
a 10-week project, then our
plan value is that we should
have completed 50% of the work.
Now, let me just take a little sidebar
here.
For the purpose of the PMP exam and only
the PNP exam, it doesn't work in reality,
right?
You always assume
that your planned value is
going to be spread
across your project linearly.
It's always a straight line relationship,
right?
So it's not necessary, so in reality it's
going to be an S curve, right?
But for the purpose of the PMP exam,
right, you always assume that when they're
asking you about planned value, it's
going to be spread across your project.
Line, it's going to be a straight line
relationship.
They're just testing your
knowledge and understanding
of the terms and formula
more than anything else.
If we're on a 10-week project,
each week we should have completed
one-tenth of the work and spent one-tenth
of the budget.
If we're on a one-year project,
each month, we should have completed
1-12th of the work and spent 1-12th of the
budget.
So in this case, then, it's a 10-week
project costing $100,000.
So each week we should be doing $10,000
worth of work, right?
So basically doing one-tenth of the work
and spending $10,000 a week.
So if we are five weeks into a 10-week
project, then what would our plan value be?
Simply $50,000.
Right, we have five weeks.
So we're five-tenths
of the way through the
project, 50% of the way
through the project, right?
So a plan value is $50,000.
Right?
So that would be our plan value here.
or another way of
looking at this, each week
we should be doing $10,000 worth of work.
So five weeks time $10,000, $50,000.
So that's what we should have done.
That's our plan value.
Earned value, on the other hand,
is at the same point in time, where we are
right now, how much dollars worth of work
have we actually done?
What have we actually accomplished at this
point in time?
So it says here in our, question that we
are 40% complete.
We should be 50% complete.
We should be five weeks and 10 week
project.
But let's say we're only 40% complete.
Right.
So we have done 40% of the entire project.
The entire project is costing 100,000.
We've done 40%.
So earned value is simply 40% of 100,000.
Now, if we look at these two terms,
plan value, earned value, just as a side
note, we should have completed $50,000
worth of work.
That's our plan value.
We should have completed $50,000 worth of
work.
But our earned value says we have actually
completed $40,000 worth of work.
What does this tell you about your
project?
Just by looking at the
numbers, we should have done
50,000, we've actually done
40,000, we're behind schedule.
And in fact, we're behind schedule.
If we compare the number, where they're
actually behind schedule by $10,000.
That's something called Schedule Variance,
which we're going to
cover in another video.
So basically, by understanding,
just by looking at, and understanding
these terms, looking at these numbers,
you can, and the key is understanding,
you can see that we are behind schedule.
Now, actual cost, actual cost is how much
have we actually spent so far?
So we have spent $60,000.
It tells us in the question.
In this case, it tells us in the question
we have spent $60,000.
So now let's look at this.
Earned value is saying that we are 40%
complete, right?
That's our earned value.
We are 40% complete.
So if we are 40% complete, we should have
done $40,000 worth of work.
Our actual cost here is saying that we
have spent $60,000, right?
So in our scenario, it says we spent
$60,000.
so far.
In doing $40,000 worth of work.
So what we have accomplished so far is we
are 40% complete.
We have done $40,000 worth of work.
Okay, so we're behind schedule.
We've understood that.
But in doing $40,000 worth of work,
we should have spent $40,000.
But we haven't.
We have spent $60,000.
By looking at these two numbers,
what are that telling us?
It's telling us we're over-budget.
Right.
And in this case, we should have spent
40,000.
We've actually spent 60,000.
It's showing us that we're $20,000 over
budget.
That is actually another formula.
That's a formula called schedule variance.
Again, schedule variance is covered in
another video.
But just by looking at these two numbers,
you can see that we are over budget.
So looking between the plan
value and earned value, plan
value is what we should
have done at this point in time.
Earned value is what we've actually done
at this point in time, the difference is
showing how much ahead of schedule or
behind schedule we are.
With earned value and the actual cost,
when you're comparing these two numbers,
earned value is this is what
we've actually accomplished,
and therefore that's what
we should have spent.
Actual cost is what we've actually spent.
So the difference in these
two then is going to be
showing you how much over
budget or under budget we are.
Again, at this point in time.
Okay, So these are the three basic terms
here, right?
So three basic earned value terms.
Plan value, earned value actual cost.
If you understand these
three basic terms, some
of those other terms
start falling into place.